According to the weather forecast,
気象予報士によると
due to radiative cooling or
a cold air mass or something,
今朝の気温は放射冷却とか　上空の寒気が原因とかで
真冬並みの冷え込みだったらしい
this morning's temperature would
be as cold as the middle of winter.
It wasn't until I started riding
my Cub that I noticed,
カブに乗るようになって気づいた
but when riding along like this,
I was able to feel the seasons
こうして走っていると　以前よりも深く　季節を感じることができる
a lot more deeply than before.
The air that day made it feel...
as though I were swimming in ice.
その日の空気はまるで
氷の中を泳いでいるようだった
"In Ice"
"Super Cub Episode 9"
The air that day made it feel...
as though I were swimming in ice.
"In Ice"
"Super Cub Episode 9"
初めての小さな旅路
目的地ならいらないよ
何もない私の頬に
手招きするように風が吹く
寄り道　回り道
いつもの景色も鮮やかに
右手をひねるたび　何度でも胸が弾むから
さあ　ギアを上げて　顔を上げて
どこまでも伸びてく道だって
昨日より少し遠くまで
きみとなら怖くない　どこだって
私ひとりでは　作れない風だ
Ah... now that's warm.
あったか～い
"2nd Year"
We have to do something.
なんとかしないとね
Something... Yeah, something.
なんとか… そう　なんとかね
やっぱり　アレを買うしかないかも
We really... might not have
any choice but to buy those.
アレだけは絶対嫌　カッコ悪い！
No, anything but those. They're so uncool.
But I think it's our best option.
でも　アレが最良の方法だと思う
Even so! There's no way I'm buying one.
それでも！アレだけは絶対に買わない
It's even starting to get
too cold for this, too.
さすがにここも寒くなってきたわね
Ah... Your mess tin is cooking
your rice just fine, huh?
メスティン　うまく炊けてるじゃない
Mm-hmm.
うん
Excuse me... would it be okay...
if I ate with you?
あの…
一緒に食べても… いいですか？
Mm-hmm.
うん
はい　あったかいですよ
Here. It's nice and hot.
Thanks.
ありがとう
Here, for you, too, Reiko-chan.
はい　礼子ちゃんも
ありがとう！
Thanks.
Tè al latte.
テ・アル・ラテ
イタリア風のミルクティーです
It's Italian milk tea. It's chilly today,
so I added a little grappa, too.
今日は寒いので　グラッパを少し入れました
"Caution: too much makes it
alcoholic and actionable"
It's Italian milk tea. It's chilly today,
so I added a little grappa, too.
グラッパ？
"Caution: too much makes it
alcoholic and actionable"
"Grappa"?
"Caution: too much makes it
alcoholic and actionable"
It's a brandy distilled from
leftover wine pomace.
ワインのブドウ粕から作ったブランデーです
Stand up a minute.
ちょっと立って
Huh?
ちょ　ちょっと… 礼子ちゃん!?
H-Hey...
Reiko-chan?
大丈夫　積める
It's okay. You can fit.
Shii-chan, if I stuff you into
the rear box of my Hunter Cub,
椎ちゃんをハンターカブのリアボックスに押し込んでおけば
I can enjoy some hot coffee
or milk tea anytime.
私はいつでもあったかいコーヒーやミルクティーが飲める！
Huh?!
Actually, Shii-chan, are you okay
in just that coat all winter?
っていうか椎ちゃん　冬はこのコートだけで大丈夫なの？
Huh?
モールトンに乗ってるときも？
Even while you're riding your Moulton?
うん　これだけでそんなに寒くないけど
Mm-mm, I'm not that
cold wearing just this.
Hmm...
あの…
Um, if you're cold, couldn't
you wear something more?
寒いなら　何か着ればいいんじゃないですか？
買い替えるのは難しい
It's a struggle for me
to buy something else.
This is all she has.
これっていうものがない
I see...
そうですか
I think I might have
something that can help!
もしかしたらなんとかなるかもしれません
ただいま～
I'm home!
Ah, welcome!
やぁ　いらっしゃい
どうも
Hello.
Wait here a minute.
ちょっと待ってて
How would you like some
Mandheling high roast today?
今日はマンデリンのハイローストなんてどうかな？
Oh... Yeah, that.
あぁ… それで
Yes, please.
お願いします
Sorry to keep you.
お待たせしました
This is it.
これなんですけど
It kind of smells.
なんか臭う
Let me see that!
貸して！
This is abrasive wool, isn't it? Amazing!
I've never seen the real thing before!
これ　アブラッシヴ・ウールじゃない？
すごい… 本物見るの初めて！
Ab-- What?
アブ…？
Abrasive wool.
アブラッシヴ・ウール
羊から刈り取られたまま　最低限の脱脂しかしていないウールだ
It's wool that has the bare
minimum washing done
after it is sheared from the sheep.
Hunters in the Rocky Mountains
and the cold regions of Canada
ロッキー山脈やカナダの寒冷地で活動するハンターは
don't trust cold-weather gear with liners
that use anything other than this wool.
このウール以外で作られた防寒インナーを決して信用しない
The same with Burt Munro,
who rode the world's fastest Indian!
「世界最速のインディアン」に乗っていた　バート・マンローもそう！
最新素材のレーシングスーツじゃなく
His racing suit wasn't made
from the latest materials;
he wore New Zealand wool
as he raced along the salt flats!
ニュージーランドのウールを着て塩湖を走ったのよ
バイクには似合わないような
It doesn't seem suited to motorbikes.
We can use this cardigan to make
a liner to fit under your jacket.
そのカーディガンで　小熊さんのジャケットの裏地　ライナーを作るんですよ
And with the leftover wool, we can make
some stockings for you, Reiko-chan.
ほどいて余ったウールで　礼子ちゃんには靴下を作るとか
I'd like that.
それいい！
Is that okay, Papa?
いいよね？パパ！
You've only worn it a few times
since I bought it for you.
買ったっきり何回か着ただけだからな
If you're going to wear it,
I'd be glad to let you have it.
着てくれる人がいるなら　喜んで譲るけど
Reiko...
礼子
What do you think?
どうですか？
It's warm.
暖かい
I will take it.
これ　もらいます
You have to add some oil
whenever you wash it.
洗うたびに油を足さなきゃいけないんだよ？
ラノリンオイルを溶かしたお湯に漬け込まなきゃいけなかったり
That means soaking it in hot water
with lanolin oil mixed in.
It's quite a bit of trouble.
いろいろ面倒も多い
I can trust things that are trouble.
面倒なものは信頼できます
I wasn't able to get much out of it,
but if it can find new life with you...
私には活かすことはできなかったけど
君の元で蘇らせてもらえるなら
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
Okay, start making it.
じゃあ早速作って
Huh?
私　てっきり小熊さんは裁縫ができるのかと
I was sure that you
would be able to sew it.
You do your own maintenance
on your motorbike, and all.
バイクの整備もできちゃうくらいだし
I can't.
できない
Huh? Papa?
え～っ！パパ！
No way, no way! About all
I can do is sew on buttons.
無理無理
私はボタン付けぐらいしかできないし
And Mama can't even do that.
ママはそれもできない
Hmm?
Let's go to the school, right now.
今から学校に行こう
Do you have an idea in mind?
何か思いついたことがあるのかな？
うまくいけば　今日中になんとかなるかもしれません
If things go right, we may be
able to deal with this today.
Well, we'd better hurry. Let's take care
of this before they close the front gate.
じゃ急がないとね
校門が閉まる前に片づけましょ
Reiko-chan?
礼子ちゃん？
Does she have a helmet?
ヘルメットありませんか？
If the one that she used in middle school
will work, then there is that one.
椎が中学時代に使ってたものなら　あるにはあるけど
Here.
はい
Huh?
You're fine, I tell you.
大丈夫だって
Too fast!
速い～！
Turn a cardigan into a liner?
カーディガンをライナーに？
それと靴下！
Also some stockings!
If we don't, we might freeze to death.
できないと　凍え死んでしまうかもしれません
I don't know about that. Why don't
you show me the material first?
大げさねぇ
とりあえず　材料を見せてもらおうかしら
This is it.
これです
No way! Abrasive wool?!
ウソ!? アブラッシヴ・ウール！
If we can't make a liner out of it,
it might have to be thrown out.
ライナーにならないなら　捨てるしかないかも
だめよ　もったいない！
No, that would be a waste! Fine,
since my students' health depends on this,
いいわ　生徒の健康に関わるものですからね
I'll do it.
やりましょう
じゃまたな
お疲れっした～
お疲れした～
--See you tomorrow!
There.
はい
Wow!
ジッパーだと　下に着る服とか肌を傷つけちゃうから
A zipper might hurt whatever you
wear under it, or even your skin,
so I went with buttons instead.
ボタン留めにしたの
I used rubber buttons, like they use
on real rugby shirts, not the fake kind.
偽物じゃない本物のラガーシャツに使われている　ゴム製のボタンを使ったわ
Oh, yeah?
And... here are the stockings.
で…
はい　靴下
And also... Here, a thermos cozy.
それと…
はい　ポットカバー
Is that something you can use?
こんなのでよかったかしら？
Yes!
はい！
If there's anything else
you need, just say so.
また必要なものがあったら　言ってね
I'll handle all of your woolen needs.
毛糸のことなら私に任せて
ありがとうございました！
--Thank you very much!
靴下はどう？
Do you like your stockings?
Mm, they're pretty nice.
かなりいい感じ
And how is your liner?
ライナーはどうですか？
Very good. I should be fine with
the cold for a while like this.
すごくいい
これならしばらく寒さも大丈夫そう
Now for the weather forecast.
続いて天気予報です
甲府地方気象台の発表によりますと
Reports from the Kofu Local
Meteorological Office
say that Mt. Fuji has had its
first snowfall of the season.
富士山で初冠雪が観測されました
気象庁の地域気象観測システムによると…
According to the Meteorological
Agency's AMeDAS System...
The wool liner alone isn't enough anymore.
ウールライナーだけじゃもうだめだ
That's the thing about cold-weather gear.
防寒装備はね　その性能を超えた冷気が来ると
Once it gets colder than it can handle,
it just gives up on you.
あっさり降参するのよ
いよいよアレを買うしか…
I don't think we can put off
buying those anymore.
No way! They're so ugly!
I'm not putting one on my Hunter Cub!
嫌よ　カッコ悪い！
私のハンターカブには付けない！
But there's nothing else we can do now.
でも　もう他に方法はない
--Good morning!
--I'm never buying one!
おはようございま～す
絶対に買わない！
Are you heading out somewhere?
どこかへ出かけるんですか？
Just a little shopping.
ちょっと買い物に
We still haven't decided to buy anything!
まだ買うって決めてない！
Please stop by the shop!
I'll have hot coffee waiting for you!
お店来てくださいね！
コーヒーいれて待ってますから～！
We really don't have any
choice but to install them--
やっぱり　もうアレを付けるしかない…
No way. If it comes to putting
one of those on my Cub,
嫌だ
私のカブにあんなもの付けるくらいなら
I'd rather keep it locked up
over the winter.
冬の間カブを封印する！
I don't really want to put one on, either.
私も本当は付けたくない
Even a used one is expensive,
and I can't buy a new one.
中古でも高いし　新品なんて買えない
So warm...!
あったか～い
There it is.
あった
A windshield.
ウインドシールド
Are you buying it?
買うの？
"Super Cub Windshield"
Excuse me a second.
ちょいとごめんよ
"Checkout"
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございました～
Excuse me.
すみません
Do you have any more
windshields for a Super Cub?
スーパーカブ用のウインドシールドってまだありますか？
Oh, we just sold our last one.
今ので売り切れですね
How about one that would fit a Hunter Cub?
ハンターカブに取り付け可能なやつはどうですか？
Hmm... I don't see anything here.
う～ん…
今は取り扱いがないですね
Thank goodness. If they had one,
I might have lost my head and bought it.
よかった
もしあったら　気の迷いで買っちゃってたかもしれない
Me, too.
私も　後先考えずに散財してたかも
I would have thrown my money away
without thinking of the consequences.
あぁ　系列店に在庫がありますね
Oh, but one of our affiliates
has them in stock.
Would you like me to order them for you?
よかったら取り寄せますか？
They should arrive here
in two or three days.
2 ～ 3 日で届くと思いますけど
Thank you for waiting.
お待たせしました
Today I have cappuccinos for you.
今日はカプチーノです
Mmm.
うん
It has that nice brandy aroma.
ブランデーのいい香りがする
That's Uchida grappa,
made here in Yamanashi Prefecture.
山梨県産の内田グラッパですよ
"Caution: too much makes it
alcoholic and actionable"
That's Uchida grappa,
made here in Yamanashi Prefecture.
もっとたっぷり入ってるほうがいい
"Caution: too much makes it
alcoholic and actionable"
You should add even more.
"Caution: too much makes it
alcoholic and actionable"
I can't!
だめです
Just let me know when you need a refill.
お代わりが必要なときは言ってくださいね
Thanks.
ありがとう
Are you going to put a windshield on?
ウインドシールド　付けるの？
I already told you I wasn't.
だから付けないってば
They say it's the best way
to keep the cold away.
最良の防寒装備だっていうけど
So, does that mean you're putting one on?
じゃあアンタは付けるっていうの？
My budget is awfully tight this month.
予算的に今月はかなり厳しい
Um... if you're having trouble deciding,
couldn't you just try one on?
あの…
もし迷ってるなら　試着してみればいいんじゃないですか？
I actually got to use one of these
during the culture festival,
私も文化祭で実際に使ってみて
それで買おうって決めたので
and that's when I decided to buy one.
"Can I please ride one of your Cubs
with a windshield on it?"
ウインドシールド付きのカブに乗せてくださいって
We don't know anyone who would grant
such an opportunistic request.
そんな都合のいいお願いを聞いてくれる知り合いはいない
Yes, we do!
いる！
Come on!
行こう！
Huh? Right now?
えっ　今から？
大丈夫　ほら早く！
It'll be fine! Come on, hurry!
Thanks for the coffee!
ごちそうさま！
Bye.
じゃあ
See you later, Shii-chan.
じゃあね　椎ちゃん
You'll be back again, won't you?
また来てくれますよね？
If this cold keeps up, we will.
この寒さが続くなら
I sure wish it would snow.
雪が降ればいいのに
Mister!
おじさん！
Oh, what brings you here today?
おぉ　今日はどうした？
Please, can I ride one of your Cubs?
お願い！カブに乗せて！
Hmm?
All of my company bikes are out right now.
ちょうど営業車は全部出払っててな
All that's left here is this one.
今残ってるのはこいつだけなんだが
これ　事故したでしょう？
This one's been in an accident,
huh? The frame is bent.
フレームが歪んでる
Yeah, it got hit by a truck.
あぁ　トラックにぶつけられてな
Apparently the oil cap got sent
flying when it went down.
倒れたときにオイルキャップが飛んでったらしくて
Now it leaks oil. I still let it
run for a while like that,
そこからオイルが抜けてな
しばらくそのまま走ってたもんだから
ヘッドもシリンダーもだめになっちまった
and now the head and cylinders are shot.
It won't run?
走れないの？
A quick trip isn't a problem.
But it's noisy, and there's smoke.
近場を走るには問題ない
でも音うるさいし　煙吹くし
Plus its power and top speed
are both way down.
パワーも最高速もだいぶ落ちてる
Let me see the key.
キーを貸して
--Thank you very much.
ありがとうございました！
Well?
どうする？
I've made up my mind.
私はもう決めた
You did say they were ugly.
カッコ悪いって言ってた
If it works better, it's not ugly.
And you said you didn't have the money.
機能に優れたものはカッコいい
アンタも金ないって言ってた
I can live on rice and retort pouches
until my scholarship money arrives.
明日から奨学金がおりるまで
米とレトルトだけでいい
Okay.
そう…
I have to say, while the windshield was
nice on that Cub, it was a real mess.
それにしてもあのカブ
ウインドシールドはよかったけど　ひどいカブだった
He said he was about to junk it.
Why don't you go ask him for it?
もうすぐ廃車だって
もらいにいったら？
Only a fool would want that Cub.
あんなカブ欲しがるのはバカ
So Cubs are really that good, huh?
そんなにいいものなんだ　カブって
うんうん
Incredible.
すごい
Incredible! Incredible! Incredible!
すごい… すごい　すごい
Yahoo!
ヤッホー！
That day, we just kept on riding.
その日　私たちは走り続けた
Maybe it was because we were
in such high spirits,
気持ちが高揚していたからか
but after the sun went down and the
temperature fell, we both felt fine.
日が暮れて気温が下がっても　まるで平気だった
We had done a number of things
to prepare for the cold.
寒さに備えるために　いろんなことをした
We turned to a number of people for help.
いろんな人たちの力も借りた
I felt more comfortable around other
people than I had been before,
苦手だった人づきあいも　カブのためなら苦にはならない
when it was for my Cub.
Thank you very much!
ありがとうございました！
In time, autumn would pass,
and winter would arrive.
やがて秋が終わり　冬がくる
But...
けど…
I'm sure that with the bitter cold
of winter under control,
つらくて寒い冬は　きっとそれを制したとき
とても気持ちよく　おもしろいに違いない
it will no doubt feel great
and be enjoyable.
After all...
だって…
...our winterized Cubs, which we
thought would only restrain us,
私たちを縛りつけるだけだと思っていた冬のカブは
こんなにも頼もしく　可能性に満ち溢れているんだから
were as promising and
full of potential as this.
すれ違う風　未来に溶けてく
近づいてくる　優しいエンジンの音
透明だった世界に　車輪で色を付けよう
ともに駆け抜けた道
誰にも描けない私の絵になる
遠くで春が呼ぶ　すぐそこかもしれない
できるだけたくさんの　思い出連れてこう
一緒に過ごす日々　見つけた彩りは決して
色褪せない
いつだってずっと　そばにいるよ
"Super Cub Episode 10"
"Snow"
Episode 10: "Snow."
第 10 話　「雪」